[Music]
On today's video, we're going to look at
lowfat ice creams and make one that is
less than 1% fat. It's quite a
scienceheavy week this week, but
hopefully it'll help you make some
really nice zero fat ice creams.
[Music]
Low-fat and zero fat ice creams. There's
not a lot of choice uh in the stores and
those that are in stores are pretty
shockingly bad. I mean to the point
where you know I remember trying one
back in the UK and I just I couldn't eat
it. It was so bad. So I don't
traditionally make low-fat ice creams
and by low fat we mean you know gelato
down. So gelato generally starts around
6% fat content but anything below that
starts to enter into a low fat
territory. So, even 5% and below. But
there are some things that you need to
do when making these kind of ice creams.
You can't just muddle a few ingredients
together and hope for the best. It's
vastly more complicated than a luxury
standard ice cream, you know, around 10
to 13% fat and normal kind of gelato.
So, what are the things we need to look
out for? The biggest thing that we need
to look out for is the mouth feel. And
that is we we've got no cream. So the
the milk fat, the butter fat really is
the biggest contributing factor to
giving a better mouth feel on ice cream.
So once we remove that, then we've lost
all of that luxury mouth feel, that
creamy texture, it's all gone. We've
also lost a lot of solids. And that then
brings us down into the late 20% solids
without that cream. So, we need to get
our solids back up. Why do we need the
solids? Solids in ice cream really do
dictate the overall texture. If you take
a standard highfat ice cream, you know,
15%, randomly pick a number, and you
you've got a really nice scientifically
calculated balance of water, solids,
sugars, milk fats, or butter fats. and
you know the likes. Once you start
removing those, then that balance goes
out the window.
So when you remove the cream, we need to
put additional solids in from somewhere.
Now if we also look at making this with
alulose, so a sugar substitute,
we have another problem and that is the
solids that comes from sugar which is
generally a higher amount than we can
use for alulose. We've also lost more
solids. So, we start to create a watered
down, very iceheavy
frozen dessert. If you're going to get
into the ultra lowfat ice creams, then
there's a couple of things that you need
to do. One is you need to get
this maltodextrin.
Maltodextrin is a filler and it's kind
of like a starch. It's a water soluble
carbohydrate powder essentially. Um, but
it just doesn't have that calories that
the sugar has. We're going to use that
to boost our solids. We're missing a lot
of protein as well that comes from that
cream. So, we're going to add the
protein back in with vanilla protein
powder. You can use milk protein
derivatives. You can use any flavor
protein powder. We're going to make a
vanilla ice cream here. And skim milk
powder that is also a excellent source
of milk proteins. So don't ever forget
that as a protein source.
But obviously the milk powder comes with
a lot of lactose. That lactose is
calories. So we can't use just milk
powder. Number one, that flavor will
overpower everything else. And number
two, the extreme amount of lactose in
there will just bring the calories up.
Obviously lactose just being a type of
sugar. So we need to balance that out.
Now, we're going to stabilize this. This
is my 442 blend. We're going to use an
emulsifier as well. That will help
create a cohesive mix, an emulsified
blend of waters and fats, the little fat
that there is in here. We, like I said,
we're going to use alulose. Then, we're
going to put the tiniest amount of sugar
in there. Now, the sugar actually helps
create a more natural sugar taste.
Alulose actually is excellent for that.
But just a tiny little bit of sugar,
less than 1 g per 100 g, you can create
a much more natural sugar flavor without
all of the calories. A little bit of
salt just to help that freezing point.
And then our vanilla extract. This is an
alcohol- based one, but glycerin base
will also help. And if you really want
to use glycerin on its own, you can in
this and that will help a little bit
more. But it's a pretty complex recipe.
If you're into making the ultra low fat
ice creams, then I recommend you get the
multidextrin. most other things you
likely have if you're into ice cream. If
you don't, if you're not an ice cream
afficionado and you don't have all the
stuff, you're going to struggle because
you need to stabilize. You need the
emulsifier as well and you need that
multidextrin.
So, those are the kind of things that
you're going to need. Anyway, long
introduction. Let's get everything
weighed out into this pan because we're
going to need to heat it up. This is the
442 blend that I have just spoken about.
I'll do a whole other video about this
in the next week or two. So, let's just
get on and weigh everything. We're going
to start with 600 g of 2% milk in here.
Into that, we need to add 100 g of our
skim milk powder.
And into that, we're going to add 30 g
of our vanilla protein powder. We're
going to cook this off. Why are we
cooking this off? We're cooking the
protein off because we want to denature
that protein.
And denaturing protein
just means that you change the structure
after heating it. And by changing the
structure, you can create a thicker mix.
And we absolutely need that here. It
will it happens when you cook egg yolks.
You're denaturing the proteins in there
and enabling them to bond with the other
protein within the mix and create a new
structure, which is the increased
viscosity. We absolutely need that here
more than any other recipe you're ever
going to make. So, with our protein in
there, and during the editing, I
realized that the part where it added
the multidextrin wasn't recorded. So,
make sure you add that at the same time
that you add your skim milk powder.
We're going to go in with our alulose.
We're going to weigh this separately
because I want to put
my stabilizer in here with it and my
emulsifier.
There isn't enough in here.
150 gram of alios. One of these is this
is powdered and that one is granular.
Doesn't make any difference, but
if you buy alos, you're going to get
what you get. So, into that, we're going
to add in our stabilizer blend. And
we're going to go for 4 g, which is a
lot, but it's required. And into that,
we're going to add 2 g of
emulsifier. This is sunflower
lesserithin. You can use soy less thin.
Actually, I prefer soy less thin, but
some people have the soy allergies. So,
just uh think about what you're doing.
You can also use liquid sunflower or soy
less thin. That is absolutely fine.
We're going to stir all this together.
Lesserithin powder creates these like
super hard lumps. So, it's good to mix
it up with other powders because you can
just get rid of those lumps. Like that.
In that little bunch goes inulin. Inulin
is another
product that you are going to need if
you make plant-based ice creams or
lowfat ice creams because it again is
um a different kind of bulking agent and
it is often used and I use it quite a
lot in recipes where I don't want to add
the skim milk powder and it reduces that
lactose. Inulin comes from chory root
fiber. And we're going to add nearly
five grams of normal sugar. Finally,
little pinch of salt. That's probably an
eighth of a teaspoon. And finally, we're
going to add in
water. We're going to have 34 g. And
that is to And that's cuz this is going
to thicken up a lot when we cook it,
which is what we're going to do now.
We're going to leave our vanilla extract
for the end. So on the hob, we're going
to heat this up to 85 C, which is 185 F,
and then bring it back and do the last
little bit. So this base has thickened
up considerably. It's it's like a super
thick
custard style base now cuz we've
denatured all those proteins. That's
essential to increase viscosity so that
we get a better mouth feel. But we have
one more thing to add. But just stir
this for a couple of minutes cuz you
will don't want to put vanilla extract
in or any extract. So if you make this
with
unflavored protein powder, then you can
use any extract to flavor this. So but
if you use alcohol based extracts, if
you put it in too hot at 85C, all that
alcohol will burn off. We absolutely
need that alcohol to change the freezing
point of our ice cream. You can either
stir it for a few minutes or pop it in a
container and let it cool down and put
it in the end. So, what we're going to
do here is we're going to put this into
our container. Couple of things to be
aware of. Don't be afraid if this goes
super super thick in the fridge. It
will. Um, but we will break that back up
when it comes to churning. So, with that
in mind, smells delicious. Smells just
like vanilla custard. Smells like birds
custard.
That is now going to go in the fridge to
cool down. And then when it's cool,
we'll put this in.
So now that it's cool, we're going to
get our vanilla extract out. This is
Mexican vanilla extract. It's really
good, but as you can see, it's super
super thick. And that is okay. That is
totally expected in this recipe because
it's basically zero fat, zero sugar, but
that actually doesn't make any
difference. We're going to thin it down
with a little bit of milk. So just take
that. It's about 30 gish, 30 ms. You
have a little bit of freedom to thin
that down with a little bit more if you
want to, but we're going to whisk that
together. And then we're going to add in
our vanilla extract, which I didn't
record for some random reason. And we're
going to pop it into our pre- chilled
machine to churn. It looks, as you can
see, super super thick, and it
absolutely is, but the magic is going to
come when it starts to churn. So, you
can see here, really silky soft texture
coming through. Good over. We're going
to scoop it out. And again, it's a very
unusual texture to most luxury ice
creams. This really is a oneoff. But now
that it's in the container, it's going
in the freezer. We're going to get some
dished up. Wait until you see this
scoop.
It's perfect. It's actually could do
with maybe an hour more in the freezer,
but even now after over a week, it
scoops perfectly. Delicious looking ice
cream. Super smooth, decadent texture.
Let's try it.
So, there we go. a an ice cream with
basically zero fat.
Actually got surprising good overrun
from it.
That is not half bad.
Nice vanilla flavor come through. Good
texture. Airy, too. So that that's um
that's really good. If you've ever
bought a low fat or super low fat ice
cream from the supermarket, then you
know how bad they actually are. Give
this one a try and you will be really
surprised how good this is in comparison
to a lot of other ice creams. The base
is really thick when you take it out of
the fridge and it's chilled down. That
is fine. Use that little bit of milk, 30
mil to thin that back down. Add your
vanilla extract at that same time. Don't
forget like I did. And you'll be
surprised how well that churns. You can
do this with a lot of other flavors.
Obviously, if you use vanilla protein
powder, then it kind of makes sense to
make a vanilla flavored version of this.
But if you use chocolate protein powder,
then you can turn this into a chocolate
ice cream. And the the list goes on. So,
if you want to make an ice cream that is
less than 1% fat, has less than 450
calories per pint, and actually with the
overrun, I'll need to recalculate
recalculate, but I'll put the
nutritional breakdown on the screen
here. It's super low calorie, especially
with zero sugar as well. Bit of a
sciency video for those that might not
be interested. But thanks very much for
watching. Don't forget to like and
subscribe.
See you next week.
[Music]